On my desk in my office, I keep a small clay pot
Na biurku trzymam  małe gliniane naczynie,
that I made in college. It's raku, which is a kind of pottery
zrobione na studiach. To jest raku,  rodzaj wyrobu ceramicznego,
that began in Japan centuries ago as a way of
który powstał w Japonii jako technika
making bowls for the Japanese tea ceremony.
wyrobu miseczek  do ceremonii parzenia herbaty.
This one is more than 400 years old.
To naczynie ma ponad 400 lat.
Each one was pinched or carved out of a ball of clay,
Każde z nich zostało wyrzeźbione z gliny,
and it was the imperfections that people cherished.
a najbardziej ceniono w nich  niedoskonałości.
Everyday pots like this cup take eight to 10 hours to fire.
Naczynia codziennego użytku  wypala się 10 godzin.
I just took this out of the kiln last week, and the kiln itself
Ten wyjęłam z pieca  w zeszłym tygodniu.
takes another day or two to cool down, but raku
Piec stygnie kolejny dzień lub dwa.
is really fast. You do it outside, and you take the kiln
Wypalanie raku trwa krótko.  Stojący na dworze piec
up to temperature. In 15 minutes, it goes to 1,500 degrees,
rozgrzewa się do 1500 stopni  w 15 minut,
and as soon as you see that the glaze has melted inside,
a gdy szkliwo stopi się w piecu,
you can see that faint sheen, you turn the kiln off,
widać słaby połysk  i można wyłączyć piec.
and you reach in with these long metal tongs,
Długimi metalowymi szczypcami  wyciągamy naczynie.
you grab the pot, and in Japan, this red-hot pot
W Japonii garnuszek  rozgrzany do czerwoności
would be immediately immersed in a solution of green tea,
zostałby od razu włożony  do wywaru zielonej herbaty.
and you can imagine what that steam would smell like.
Możecie sobie wyobrazić zapach pary.
But here in the United States, we ramp up the drama
W USA robimy to bardziej dramatycznie
a little bit, and we drop our pots into sawdust,
i wrzucamy garnek w trociny,  które zajmują się ogniem.
which catches on fire, and you take a garbage pail,
Wtedy przykrywamy je  kubłem na śmieci,
and you put it on top, and smoke starts pouring out.
spod którego zaczyna  sączyć się się dym.
I would come home with my clothes reeking of woodsmoke.
Od moich ubrań jechało dymem.
I love raku because it allows me to play with the elements.
Kocham raku, bo pozwala mi  bawić się żywiołami.
I can shape a pot out of clay and choose a glaze,
Mogę ukształtować garnek z gliny  i wybrać glazurę,
but then I have to let it go to the fire and the smoke,
ale potem muszę wypuścić go  w ogień i dym.
and what's wonderful is the surprises that happen,
Najwspanialsze w tym są takie niespodzianki,
like this crackle pattern, because it's really stressful
jak spękana powierzchnia,  bo garnki poddawane są
on these pots. They go from 1,500 degrees
dużym naprężeniom.  Z temperatury 1500 stopni
to room temperature in the space of just a minute.
stygną do temperatury pokojowej  w ciągu minuty.
Raku is a wonderful metaphor for the process of creativity.
Raku to cudowna metafora kreatywności.
I find in so many things that tension between
W wielu rzeczach  istnieje napięcie pomiędzy tym,
what I can control and what I have to let go
co mogę kontrolować  i tym, co muszę odpuścić.
happens all the time, whether I'm creating a new radio show
bez względu na to,  czy tworzę nowy program radiowy,
or just at home negotiating with my teenage sons.
czy negocjuję z nastoletnimi synami.
When I sat down to write a book about creativity,
Pisząc książkę o kreatywności
I realized that the steps were reversed.
zdałam sobie sprawę,  że proces trzeba odwrócić.
I had to let go at the very beginning, and I had to
Na samym początku musiałam odpuścić
immerse myself in the stories of hundreds of artists
i zanurzyć się w historiach setek artystów,
and writers and musicians and filmmakers, and as I listened
pisarzy, muzyków i filmowców.
to these stories, I realized that creativity
Zrozumiałam, że kreatywność
grows out of everyday experiences
wyrasta z codziennych doświadczeń,
more often than you might think, including
częściej niż nam się zdaje,
letting go.
włączając w to odpuszczanie.
It was supposed to break, but that's okay. (Laughter) (Laughs)
Miało się rozbić, ale tak też jest dobrze. (Śmiech)
That's part of the letting go, is sometimes it happens
To część odpuszczania: czasem się zdarza,
and sometimes it doesn't, because creativity also grows
a czasem nie, bo kreatywność
from the broken places.
wyrasta także z potłuczonych kawałków.
The best way to learn about anything
Najlepszym sposobem  na naukę czegokolwiek
is through stories, and so I want to tell you a story
są opowiadania. Chcę opowiedzieć historię
about work and play and about four aspects of life
o pracy, zabawie i o czterech aspektach życia,
that we need to embrace
które musimy przyswoić,
in order for our own creativity to flourish.
aby nasza kreatywność kwitła.
The first embrace is something that we think,
Pierwszy aspekt z początku  wydaje się bardzo łatwy,
"Oh, this is very easy," but it's actually getting harder,
ale z czasem staje cię coraz trudniejszy.
and that's paying attention to the world around us.
Chodzi o poświęcanie uwagi temu,  co nas otacza.
So many artists speak about needing to be open,
Wielu artystów mówi o potrzebie otwartości,
to embrace experience, and that's hard to do when
przyjmowaniu doświadczeń. To niełatwe,
you have a lighted rectangle in your pocket that
kiedy świecący prostokąt w kieszeni
takes all of your focus.
zajmuje ci całą uwagę.
The filmmaker Mira Nair speaks about growing up
Filmowiec Mira Nair mówi o dorastaniu
in a small town in India. Its name is Bhubaneswar,
w Bhubaneswar, małym miasteczku w Indiach.
and here's a picture of one of the temples in her town.
Oto zdjęcie jednej ze świątyń w mieście.
Mira Nair: In this little town, there were like 2,000 temples.
Mira Nair: W miasteczku było ze 2000 świątyń.
We played cricket all the time. We kind of grew up
Graliśmy w krykieta. Dorastaliśmy w gruzie.
in the rubble. The major thing that inspired me,
Moją główną inspiracją,
that led me on this path, that made me a filmmaker eventually,
dzięki której jestem dziś filmowcem,
was traveling folk theater that would come through the town
był podróżny teatr ludowy. Przyjeżdżali do miasta,
and I would go off and see these great battles
a ja oglądałam zmagania dobra ze złem,
of good and evil by two people in a school field
przedstawiane przez dwie osoby  na boisku szkolnym,
with no props but with a lot of, you know,
bez rekwizytów, ale z ogromną pasją
passion, and hashish as well, and it was amazing.
i haszyszem. To było cudowne.
You know, the folk tales of Mahabharata and Ramayana,
Opowieści ludowe z dwóch świętych ksiąg
the two holy books, the epics that everything comes out of
Mahabharaty i Ramajany, z których ponoć wszystko się w Indiach wywodzi.
in India, they say. After seeing that Jatra, the folk theater,
Po zobaczeniu Jatry, tego teatru ludowego,
I knew I wanted to get on, you know, and perform.
wiedziałam, że muszę iść i występować.
Julie Burstein: Isn't that a wonderful story?
Julie Burstein: Czy nie jest to wspaniała historia?
You can see the sort of break in the everyday.
Widać rodzaj odskoczni od codzienności.
There they are in the school fields, but it's good and evil,
Na szkolnym boisku znalazło się dobro i zło,
and passion and hashish. And Mira Nair was a young girl
pasja i haszysz. Mira Nair była młodą dziewczyną,
with thousands of other people watching this performance,
wśród tysięcy innych widzów,
but she was ready. She was ready to open up
ale ona była gotowa. Była otwarta na iskrę,
to what it sparked in her, and it led her,
która, jak sama powiedziała,
as she said, down this path to become
poprowadziła ją ku karierze
an award-winning filmmaker.
nagradzanego filmowca.
So being open for that experience that might change you
Otwartość na doświadczenie,  które może nas zmienić,
is the first thing we need to embrace.
jest pierwszą rzeczą, którą musimy pojąć.
Artists also speak about how some of their most powerful work
Artyści mówią także o tym,  jak ich największe dzieła
comes out of the parts of life that are most difficult.
rodzą się z najtrudniejszych elementów życia.
The novelist Richard Ford speaks about
Pisarz Richard Ford mówi o wyzwaniu z dzieciństwa,
a childhood challenge that continues to be something
z którym zmaga się do dziś.
he wrestles with today. He's severely dyslexic.
Ma poważny problem z dysleksją.
Richard Ford: I was slow to learn to read, went all the way
Richard Ford: Nauka czytania szła mi bardzo wolno,
through school not really reading more than the minimum,
kończąc szkołę czytałem  na minimalnym poziomie
and still to this day can't read silently
i dotąd ciche czytanie  nie idzie mi wiele szybciej,
much faster than I can read aloud,
niż czytanie na głos,
but there were a lot of benefits to being dyslexic for me
ale dysleksja miała dla mnie wiele plusów.
because when I finally did reconcile myself to how slow
Kiedy pogodziłem się z tym,  że muszę czytać powoli,
I was going to have to do it, then I think I came very slowly
zacząłem chyba z wolna doceniać
into an appreciation of all of those qualities of language
wszystkie zalety języka i zdań,
and of sentences that are not just the cognitive
nie tylko poznawcze aspekty języka,
aspects of language: the syncopations, the sounds of words,
jak synkopy, dźwięk słów,
what words look like, where paragraphs break,
wygląd słów, umiejscowienie akapitów,
where lines break. I mean, I wasn't so badly dyslexic that
łamanie linijek. Nie miałem aż takiej dysleksji,
I was disabled from reading. I just had to do it
żeby nie móc w ogóle czytać.  Musiałem tylko robić to
really slowly, and as I did, lingering on those sentences
bardzo powoli. Czołgając się przez zdania
as I had to linger, I fell heir to language's other qualities,
odziedziczyłem inne wartości języka,
which I think has helped me write sentences.
co pomogło mi pisać zdania.
JB: It's so powerful. Richard Ford, who's won the Pulitzer Prize,
JB: To takie przejmujące. Richard Ford,  laureat Nagrody Pulitzera,
says that dyslexia helped him write sentences.
mówi, że dysleksja  pomogła mu pisać zdania.
He had to embrace this challenge, and I use that word
Musiał przyjąć to wyzwanie  i używam tego słowa celowo.
intentionally. He didn't have to overcome dyslexia.
Jego zadaniem nie było pokonanie dysleksji.
He had to learn from it. He had to learn to hear the music
Musiał się od niej uczyć.  Musiał nauczyć się słyszeć
in language.
melodię języka.
Artists also speak about how pushing up against
Artyści mówią także o tym,  jak przekraczanie własnych ograniczeń,
the limits of what they can do, sometimes pushing
a czasem dotarcie do granic możliwości,
into what they can't do, helps them focus
pomaga im skupić się
on finding their own voice.
na odnalezieniu własnego głosu.
The sculptor Richard Serra talks about how,
Rzeźbiarz Richard Serra opowiada,
as a young artist, he thought he was a painter,
że jako młody artysta  uważał się za malarza
and he lived in Florence after graduate school.
i po skończeniu szkoły  mieszkał we Florencji.
While he was there, he traveled to Madrid,
W tym czasie wybrał się do Madrytu,
where he went to the Prado to see this picture
gdzie poszedł do Muzeum Prado,
by the Spanish painter Diego Velázquez.
zobaczyć obraz Diego Velazqueza
It's from 1656, and it's called "Las Meninas,"
z 1656 r. pod tytułem "Las Meninas",
and it's the picture of a little princess
który przedstawia małą księżniczkę
and her ladies-in-waiting, and if you look over
oraz jej damy dworu.
that little blonde princess's shoulder, you'll see a mirror,
Za jasnowłosą księżniczką widać lustro.
and reflected in it are her parents, the King and Queen
Lustro odbija jej rodziców,  króla i królową Hiszpanii,
of Spain, who would be standing where you might stand
którzy staliby tam, gdzie dzisiaj
to look at the picture.
stoicie wy, patrząc na obraz.
As he often did, Velázquez put himself in this painting too.
Velazquez swoim zwyczajem  umieścił na obrazie również siebie.
He's standing on the left with his paintbrush in one hand
Stoi po lewej stronie, z pędzlem w jednej ręce
and his palette in the other.
i z paletą w drugiej.
Richard Serra: I was standing there looking at it,
Richard Serra: Stałem tam, patrząc na niego,
and I realized that Velázquez was looking at me,
i zrozumiałem, że Velazquez patrzy na mnie.
and I thought, "Oh. I'm the subject of the painting."
Pomyślałem: "Ja jestem tematem tego obrazu.
And I thought, "I'm not going to be able to do that painting."
Nie dam rady tak malować".
I was to the point where I was using a stopwatch
W tamtym okresie używałem nawet stopera
and painting squares out of randomness,
i malowałem przypadkowe kwadraty,
and I wasn't getting anywhere. So I went back and dumped
zmierzałem donikąd. Wyrzuciłem wszystkie obrazy
all my paintings in the Arno, and I thought, I'm going to just start playing around.
do rzeki. Postanowiłem zacząć się bawić.
JB: Richard Serra says that so nonchalantly, you might
JB: Serra mówi to tak nonszalancko, że można tego nie uchwycić.
have missed it. He went and saw this painting by a guy
Zobaczył obraz gościa,
who'd been dead for 300 years, and realized,
który nie żyje od 300 lat, i zrozumiał,
"I can't do that," and so Richard Serra went back
że sam tak nie potrafi. Wrócił do studia
to his studio in Florence, picked up all of his work
we Florencji, wziął wszystkie swoje prace
up to that point, and threw it in a river.
i wrzucił je do rzeki.
Richard Serra let go of painting at that moment,
Richard Serra odpuścił sobie malarstwo,
but he didn't let go of art. He moved to New York City,
ale nie sztukę.  Przeprowadził się do Nowego Jorku,
and he put together a list of verbs
i spisał ponad 100 czasowników:
— to roll, to crease, to fold —
"zwijać, zgnieść, złożyć",
more than a hundred of them, and as he said,
i zgodnie z obietnicą zaczął się bawić.
he just started playing around. He did these things
Oddawał słowa w różnych materiałach.
to all kinds of material. He would take a huge sheet of lead
Brał ogromny arkusz blachy ołowianej,
and roll it up and unroll it. He would do the same thing
zwijał go i rozwijał. Robił to samo z gumą,
to rubber, and when he got to the direction "to lift,"
Przy słowie "podnosić" stworzył to,
he created this, which is in the Museum of Modern Art.
co stoi teraz w Muzeum Sztuki Nowoczesnej.
Richard Serra had to let go of painting
Richard Serra musiał porzucić malarstwo,
in order to embark on this playful exploration
aby wyruszyć na swoje radosne poszukiwania,
that led him to the work that he's known for today:
które zaowocowały dziełami,  z których dziś słynie:
huge curves of steel that require our time and motion
ogromne stalowe łuki, których doświadczenie
to experience. In sculpture,
wymaga od widza czasu i ruchu. W rzeźbie,
Richard Serra is able to do what he couldn't do in painting.
Richard Serra umie zrobić to,  czego nie mógł w malarstwie.
He makes us the subject of his art.
To my stajemy się  przedmiotem jego sztuki.
So experience and challenge
Doświadczenia, wyzwania i ograniczenia
and limitations are all things we need to embrace
trzeba najpierw zaakceptować,
for creativity to flourish.
by kreatywność mogła kwitnąć.
There's a fourth embrace, and it's the hardest.
Jest też czwarte pojęcie, najtrudniejsze.
It's the embrace of loss,
Jest to pogodzenie się ze stratą,
the oldest and most constant of human experiences.
najstarszym i najtrwalszym  ludzkim doświadczeniem.
In order to create, we have to stand in that space
Aby tworzyć, musimy stanąć pomiędzy tym,
between what we see in the world and what we hope for,
co widzimy na świecie,  a własnymi nadziejami,
looking squarely at rejection, at heartbreak,
patrząc bez emocji  na odrzucenie, zawód miłosny,
at war, at death.
wojnę, śmierć.
That's a tough space to stand in.
Bardzo ciężko stoi się w tym miejscu.
The educator Parker Palmer calls it "the tragic gap,"
Wychowawca Parker Palmer  nazywa to "tragiczną luką",
tragic not because it's sad but because it's inevitable,
nie dlatego, że budzi smutek,  ale dlatego, że jest nieunikniona.
and my friend Dick Nodel likes to say,
Mój przyjaciel Dick Nodel powtarza:
"You can hold that tension like a violin string
"Można trwać w napięciu,  jak struna w skrzypcach,
and make something beautiful."
i zrobić coś pięknego".
That tension resonates in the work of the photographer
To napięcie rezonuje  w pracach Joela Meyerowitza,
Joel Meyerowitz, who at the beginning of his career was
fotografa, który na początku kariery słynął
known for his street photography, for capturing a moment
z fotografii ulicznej,
on the street, and also for his beautiful photographs
a także z pięknych pejzaży Toskanii,
of landscapes -- of Tuscany, of Cape Cod,
czy Cape Cod,
of light.
czy światła.
Joel is a New Yorker, and his studio for many years
Joel pochodzi z Nowego Jorku i przez wiele lat
was in Chelsea, with a straight view downtown
miał studio w Chelsea, z widokiem na centrum,
to the World Trade Center, and he photographed
na World Trade Centre.
those buildings in every sort of light.
Fotografował te budynki w każdym świetle.
You know where this story goes.
Domyślacie się, dokąd zmierza ta historia.
On 9/11, Joel wasn't in New York. He was out of town,
9 września nie było go w Nowym Jorku,
but he raced back to the city, and raced down to the site
ale natychmiast wrócił i popędził
of the destruction.
na miejsce zniszczenia.
Joel Meyerowitz: And like all the other passersby,
Joel Meyerowitz: Tak jak inni przechodnie
I stood outside the chain link fence on Chambers
stałem pod siatką  przy skrzyżowaniu Chambers
and Greenwich, and all I could see was the smoke
i Greenwich. Widziałem tylko dym
and a little bit of rubble, and I raised my camera
i trochę gruzu.  Podniosłem aparat, żeby spojrzeć,
to take a peek, just to see if there was something to see,
sprawdzić tylko, czy coś widać,
and some cop, a lady cop, hit me on my shoulder,
a policjantka szturchnęła mnie w ramię
and said, "Hey, no pictures!"
i powiedziała: "Hej, żadnych zdjęć!".
And it was such a blow that it woke me up,
Ten cios mnie obudził,
in the way that it was meant to be, I guess.
w taki sposób, jak to chyba miało zadziałać.
And when I asked her why no pictures, she said,
Na pytanie, czemu nie wolno  robić zdjęć, odparła:
"It's a crime scene. No photographs allowed."
"To miejsce zbrodni.  Fotografowanie wzbronione".
And I asked her, "What would happen if I was a member
Zapytałem: "A gdybym był z prasy?"
of the press?" And she told me,
Odpowiedziała:
"Oh, look back there," and back a block was the press corps
"Patrz tam". Przecznicę dalej stali dziennikarze,
tied up in a little penned-in area,
stłoczeni na małym ogrodzonym terenie.
and I said, "Well, when do they go in?"
Zapytałem, kiedy będą mogli wejść.
and she said, "Probably never."
Odpowiedziała: "Prawdopodobnie nigdy".
And as I walked away from that, I had this crystallization,
Odchodząc stamtąd doznałem olśnienia,
probably from the blow, because it was an insult in a way.
pewnie od kuksańca,  który był rodzajem obelgi.
I thought, "Oh, if there's no pictures,
Pomyślałem: "Jeżeli nie ma zdjęć,
then there'll be no record. We need a record."
nie będzie żadnego zapisu.  Musimy mieć relację."
And I thought, "I'm gonna make that record.
I pomyślałem, że zrobię tę relację.
I'll find a way to get in, because I don't want to
Znajdę sposób, żeby się tam zostać,  bo nie chcę,
see this history disappear."
żeby ta historia zniknęła.
JB: He did. He pulled in every favor he could,
JB: Tak zrobił. Wykorzystał wszelkie kontakty
and got a pass into the World Trade Center site,
i dostał przepustkę  na teren World Trade Center,
where he photographed for nine months almost every day.
gdzie robił zdjęcia  każdego dnia, przez 9 miesięcy.
Looking at these photographs today brings back
Oglądanie ich dzisiaj  przywołuje zapach dymu,
the smell of smoke that lingered on my clothes
którymi przesiąkło mi ubranie,
when I went home to my family at night.
kiedy wracałam wieczorami do domu.
My office was just a few blocks away.
Moje biuro było tylko kilka przecznic dalej.
But some of these photographs are beautiful,
Niektóre z tych zdjęć są piękne.
and we wondered, was it difficult for Joel Meyerowitz
Czy Joel Meyerowitz miał trudności,
to make such beauty out of such devastation?
żeby stworzyć piękno  z takiego spustoszenia?
JM: Well, you know, ugly, I mean, powerful
JM: Okropne, przejmujące,
and tragic and horrific and everything, but
tragiczne i przerażające,
it was also as, in nature, an enormous event
ale na swój sposób  było to także ogromne wydarzenie,
that was transformed after the fact into this residue,
które później przekształciło się  w ten osad,
and like many other ruins
i jak wiele innych ruin,
— you go to the ruins of the Colosseum or the ruins of a cathedral someplace —
jak ruiny Koloseum  albo ruiny jakiejś katedry,
and they take on a new meaning when you watch the weather.
nabrało nowego znaczenia  przy obserwacji pogody.
I mean, there were afternoons I was down there,
Czasem przychodziłem po południu
and the light goes pink and there's a mist in the air
i światło było różowe  a powietrze zamglone,
and you're standing in the rubble, and I found myself
stałem wśród gruzu.  Zacząłem rozpoznawać
recognizing both the inherent beauty of nature
zarówno wrodzone piękno natury,
and the fact that nature, as time,
jak i fakt, że natura, podobnie jak czas,
is erasing this wound.
leczy tę ranę.
Time is unstoppable, and it transforms the event.
Niepowstrzymany czas odmienia wydarzenie.
It gets further and further away from the day,
Coraz bardziej oddala się od tamtego dnia,
and light and seasons temper it in some way,
a światło i pory roku jakoś to łagodzą.
and it's not that I'm a romantic. I'm really a realist.
Nie jestem romantykiem. Jestem realistą.
The reality is, there's the Woolworth Building
A realnie stoi tam  budynek Woolworth spowity dymem
in a veil of smoke from the site, but it's now like a scrim
co teraz wygląda  jak rozproszone światło w teatrze
across a theater, and it's turning pink,
i barwi się na różowo,
you know, and down below there are hoses spraying,
a tam poniżej woda tryska z węży,
and the lights have come on for the evening, and the water
zapalają się lampy,  woda robi się żrąco zielona
is turning acid green because the sodium lamps are on,
bo włączono lampy sodowe.
and I'm thinking, "My God, who could dream this up?"
Kto mógłby sobie wyśnić coś takiego?
But the fact is, I'm there, it looks like that,
Ale jestem tu,  wszystko właśnie tak wygląda
you have to take a picture.
i trzeba zrobić zdjęcie.
JB: You have to take a picture. That sense of urgency,
JB. Trzeba zrobić zdjęcie.  To poczucie konieczności, pracy
of the need to get to work, is so powerful in Joel's story.
jest tak silne w historii Joela.
When I saw Joel Meyerowitz recently, I told him how much
Widząc go ostatnio powiedziałam,
I admired his passionate obstinacy, his determination
że podziwiam jego zapalczywy upór, determinację,
to push through all the bureaucratic red tape to get to work,
by przepchnąć się przez biurokrację, by pracować.
and he laughed, and he said, "I'm stubborn,
Uśmiechnął się i powiedział: "Jestem uparty,
but I think what's more important
ale ważniejszy jest chyba
is my passionate optimism."
mój zapalczywy optymizm".
The first time I told these stories, a man in the audience
Kiedy opowiadałam pierwszy raz, ktoś na widowni
raised his hand and said, "All these artists talk about
podniósł rękę i powiedział:  "Ci wszyscy artyści opowiadają
their work, not their art, which has got me thinking about
o swojej pracy, a nie sztuce,  więc pomyślałem sobie
my work and where the creativity is there,
o własnej pracy i gdzie w niej  jest miejsce na kreatywność,
and I'm not an artist." He's right. We all wrestle
a nie jestem artystą".  Ma rację. Wszyscy zmagamy się
with experience and challenge, limits and loss.
z doświadczeniami i wyzwaniami,  ograniczeniami i stratami.
Creativity is essential to all of us,
Kreatywność jest niezbędna nam wszystkim,
whether we're scientists or teachers,
czy jesteśmy naukowcami, czy nauczycielami,
parents or entrepreneurs.
rodzicami, czy przedsiębiorcami.
I want to leave you with another
Chciałabym zostawić was  z jeszcze jednym obrazem
image of a Japanese tea bowl. This one
japońskiego naczynia do herbaty.
is at the Freer Gallery in Washington, D.C.
Stoi we Freer Gallery w Waszyngtonie.
It's more than a hundred years old and you can still see
Ma ponad sto lat i wciąż można zobaczyć
the fingermarks where the potter pinched it.
ślady palców garncarza.
But as you can also see, this one did break
Jak także widać, to naczynie pękło
at some point in its hundred years.
w którymś momencie  swojej stuletniej historii.
But the person who put it back together,
Osoba, która je poskładała
instead of hiding the cracks,
zamiast ukryć pęknięcia,
decided to emphasize them, using gold lacquer to repair it.
postanowiła podkreślić je złotym lakierem.
This bowl is more beautiful now, having been broken,
Pęknięta miseczka  jest teraz jeszcze piękniejsza,
than it was when it was first made,
niż w pierwotnej postaci.
and we can look at those cracks, because
Możemy popatrzyć na te pęknięcia,
they tell the story that we all live,
bo opowiadają historię  życia każdego z nas,
of the cycle of creation and destruction,
proces tworzenia i zniszczenia,
of control and letting go, of picking up the pieces
kontrolowania i odpuszczania,  zbierania fragmentów
and making something new.
i tworzenia czegoś nowego.
Thank you. (Applause)
Dziękuję. (Oklaski)